A Guide to the Records of Eastern State Hospital, 1770-2009
Library of Virginia
- Series XIV. Photographs, 1931-2007; undated., Extent: 5.425 cu. ft. (Box 56-69.)
  - Employees
    - Miscellaneous, 1977. (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978. (Box 62, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978. (Box 62, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979. (Box 62, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979. (Box 62, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980. (Box 62, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980. (Box 62, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1981. (Box 62, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1981. (Box 62, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1982. (Box 62, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1982. (Box 62, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1982. (Box 62, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1983. (Box 62, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 2009. (Box 62, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1950-1960). (Box 62, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1950-1960). (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1950-1960). (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1950-1960). (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1950-1960). (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1950-1960). (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (copies and prints), 1956; undated. (Box 63, Folder 6)
    - Physicians, 1951-1954. (Box 63, Folder 7)
    - Physicians, 1956-1971. (Box 63, Folder 8)
    - Physicians, undated. (Box 63, Folder 9)
    - Retirement of R. Lawrence Caldwell, 1975. (Box 63, Folder 10)
    - Social Services, 1953-1954; undated. (Box 63, Folder 11)
    - State hospital nursing directors, 1954. (Box 63, Folder 12)
    - Store room workers, 1953. (Box 63, Folder 13)
    - Volunteer Services / Volunteer groups, 1960-1983. (Box 63, Folder 14)
    - Volunteer Services / Volunteer groups, undated (circa 1960-1985). (Box 63, Folder 15)
    - Working with patients, 1951-1969. (Box 63, Folder 16)
    - Working with patients, 1971-1982. (Box 63, Folder 17)
    - Working with patients, undated (circa 1955; 1970). (Box 63, Folder 18)
  - Events
    - American Psychiatric Association conference, undated (circa 1979-1980). (Box 63, Folder 19)
    - American Psychiatric Association meeting (Hotel Pennsylvania), 1947. (Box 02)
    - Army and Air Force Band performances, 1973. (Box 63, Folder 20)
    - Christmas pageant, 1955. (Box 63, Folder 21)
    - Circus, 1965; 1977. (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - Eastern State Hospital 193rd anniversary, 1966. (Box 64, Folder 2)
    - Eastern State Hospital 200th anniversary, 1973. (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - Eastern State Hospital 205th anniversary, 1978. (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - Eastern State Hospital 206th anniversary, 1979. (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - Elizabeth Taylor Warner at Maryview Mental Health Center, 1980. (Box 64, Folder 6)
    - Employee picnic, 1981. (Box 64, Folder 7)
    - Employee picnic, 1982. (Box 64, Folder 8)
    - Exhibit (patient work), 1958. (Box 64, Folder 9)
    - Exhibit (Public Hospital), undated (circa 1979-1980). (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - Exhibit (unidentified), 1980. (Box 64, Folder 11)
    - Holiday Hippodrome Circus, 1973-1975; undated. (Box 64, Folder 12)
    - Horse show, 1971; 1981; undated. (Box 64, Folder 13)
    - Judicial conference, 1981. (Box 64, Folder 14)
    - July 4th party, 1949. (Box 64, Folder 15)
    - July 4th party, 1952. (Box 64, Folder 16)
    - July 4th party (rodeo), 1953. (Box 64, Folder 17)
    - July 4th party (rodeo), 1953. (Box 64, Folder 18)
    - July 4th party, 1956. (Box 64, Folder 19)
    - Labor Day party, 1948. (Box 64, Folder 20)
    - Labor Day party, 1949. (Box 64, Folder 21)
    - Labor Day party, 1951. (Box 64, Folder 22)
    - Labor Day party, 1953. (Box 64, Folder 23)
    - Mental Health Day, 1967. (Box 64, Folder 24)
    - Minstrel show, undated (circa 1950). (Box 64, Folder 25)
    - Nursing Week, 1973. (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Open House Day, 1966. (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - Picnic and fair, undated (circa 1948-1949). (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Picnic and fair, undated (circa 1948-1949). (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - "The Common Glory" choir performance, undated (circa 1949-1950). (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - Tour, 1954; undated. (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Valentine social, 1982. (Box 65, Folder 7)
    - Valentine's program, 1952. (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Week of the Aide, 1982. (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - Patients
    - Children's Unit, 1956-1969. (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - Children's Unit, 1970-1975. (Box 65, Folder 11)
    - Children's Unit, 1976-1983. (Box 65, Folder 12)
    - Children's Unit, undated (circa 1955-1965). (Box 65, Folder 13)
    - Children's Unit, undated (circa 1955-1965). (Box 65, Folder 14)
    - Children's Unit, undated (circa 1970-1982). (Box 65, Folder 15)
    - Children's Unit (album), 1977-1983. (Box 68)
    - Children's Unit (album), 1979-1983. (Box 69)
    - Children's Unit (album), undated (circa 1965-1983). (Box 69)
    - On the wards, 1963; 1975-1976. (Box 65, Folder 16)
    - On the wards, undated (circa 1950). (Box 65, Folder 17)
    - On the wards, undated (circa 1950-1955; 1980). (Box 65, Folder 18)
    - On the wards (copies and prints), 1963; undated. (Box 65, Folder 19)
    - Outdoors, undated (circa 1950-1960). (Box 65, Folder 20)
    - Statistical chart (patients under treatment, 1910-1960), 1960. (Box 65, Folder 21)
    - Transfer to Dunbar, 1953; 1968-1969. (Box 65, Folder 22)
  - Safety Department
    - Disaster drill, 1986. (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - Disaster drill, 1986. (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - Fire extinguisher training, 1983. (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - Fire test of seclusion blankets, 1986. (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - Flag pole renovation, undated (circa 1980-1985). (Box 66, Folder 5)
    - JACH meeting facility, 1986. (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1980-1985). (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - Old farm house and buildings, Demolition of, 1985. (Box 66, Folder 8)
    - Repairs to the steam line system, 1984-1985. (Box 66, Folder 9)
    - Superintendent's residence, Demolition of, 1984-1985. (Box 66, Folder 10)
    - Visitor directional signs, 1986. (Box 66, Folder 11)
    - West Dunbar buildings 4,5,6,7, Demolition of, undated (circa 1980-1985). (Box 66, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified
    - Miscellaneous, undated (circa 1950s-1970s). (Box 66, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous negatives, undated (circa 1940-1980). (Box 66, Folder 14)
- Series XV. Publications, 1844-2006., Extent: 1.575 cu. ft. (Box 70-73.)
  Contains a variety of publications ranging from articles to journals and books. Most of the publications are mental health or hospital-related. Some of the articles were written by Eastern State Hospital employees and several of the periodicals were published by the Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation and the State Hospital Board. The office that created and maintained these publications is unknown, though they may have been held by the Office of the Director or by the staff or patient libraries.
  - Subseries A. Articles and Pamphlets, 1844-2006., Extent: .675 cu. ft. (Box 70-71.)
    Contains a variety of published articles and pamphlets. The articles cover topics ranging from general mental health and awareness to very specific psychological studies. Many of the articles were written by Eastern State Hospital employees. Included here are published copies of many of Dr. John M. Galt's essays on mental health and other issues. The rough drafts of many of Dr. Galt's essays can be found in Series IV., Subseries D. Correspondence, Subject Files and Ledgers (Superintendent).
    Arranged alphabetically by author's last name.
    - Alliance for Increased Mental Health Awareness, "Changing the Face of Mental Illness in Virginia: A Sourcebook with Personal Stories about Treatment, Recovery and Support," undated, circa 1995. (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Barrett, Joseph E., M.D., "Psychiatric Facilities in Virginia and Some Neighboring States," in American Journal of Psychiatry, 1941. (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Beamer-Maxwell, Eleanor, M.D., "A Year of Symptoms, A Life Ended," in Southern Medicine and Surgery, 1950. (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Billig, Otto, M.D., "Is Schizophrenic Expression Art?: A Comparative Study of Creativeness and Schizophrenic Thinking," in The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, 1971. (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Bisconer, S.W., et. al., "Managing Aggression in a Psychiatric Hospital Using a Behaviour Plan: A Case Study," in Journal of Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing, 2006. (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Bradley, Chester D., M.D., and Caldwell, Marjorie L., R.N., "Eastern State Hospital," in Mental Health in Virginia, 1962-1963. (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - Cavey, Margaret L., "The Important Role of Nursing in Virginia's Mental Hospitals and Training Schools," in Mental Health in Virginia, 1955. (Box 70, Folder 7)
    - Colaizzi, Janet, "Seclusion and Restraint: A Historical Perspective," in Journal of Psychosocial Nursing, 2005. (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - Colaizzi, Janet, "Transorbital Lobotomy at Eastern State Hospital," in Journal of Psychosocial Nursing, 1996. (Box 70, Folder 9)
    - Duval, Addison M., M.D., "Dynamic Forces in the Public Mental Hospital," in Mental Hygiene, 1963. (Box 70, Folder 10)
    - Ebaugh, Franklin G., M.D., "Educational Possibilities of a State Psychopathic Hospital," in American Journal of Psychiatry, 1928. (Box 70, Folder 11)
    - Frierson, Bewley D., M.D., "A Preliminary Evaluation of Prochloperazine (Compazine) in Chronically Disturbed Psychotic Patients," in The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, 1958. (Box 70, Folder 12)
    - Gaines, William, H., Jr., "The Public Hospital for Disordered Minds," in Virginia Cavalcade, 1953. (Box 70, Folder 13)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "A Lecture on Idiocy," 1859. (Box 70, Folder 14)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "Essays on Asylums for Persons of Unsound Mind," Second series, 1853. (Box 70, Folder 15)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "Fragments on Insanity," in The American Journal of Insanity, 1844 October. (Box 70, Folder 16)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "Insanity in Italy," in The American Journal of Insanity, 1854 October. (Box 70, Folder 17)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "On the Medio-Legal Question of the Confinement of the Insane," in The American Journal of Insanity, 1853 January. (Box 70, Folder 18)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "On the Propriety of Admitting the Insane of the Two Sexes into the Same Lunatic Asylum," in The American Journal of Insanity, 1855 January. (Box 70, Folder 19)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "Political Essays," (includes "The Annexation of Texas" and "The Future of the Democracy"), 1852. (Box 70, Folder 20)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "Report on the Organization of Asylums for the Insane," in The American Journal of Insanity, 1850 July. (Box 70, Folder 21)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "Senile Insanity-Hypochrondriasis," in The American Journal of Insanity, 1856 January. (Box 70, Folder 22)
    - Galt, John M., M.D., "The Farm of St. Anne," in The American Journal of Insanity, 1855 April. (Box 70, Folder 23)
    - Grimes, G., "A Secret Worth Knowing: A Treatise on the Most Important Subject in the World - Simply to say, Insanity," 1845. (Box 70, Folder 24)
    - Hamlin, P.G., M.D., "Dr. John Minson Galt and the Williamsburg Asylum," in Virginia Medical Monthly, 1941 September. (Box 70, Folder 25)
    - Harris, Collier C., "The Treatment of Mental Deficiency in Colonial Virginia," in Virginia Cavalcade, 1971. (Box 70, Folder 26)
    - Jones, Granville L., M.D., "Mental Illness in Medical Practice," undated. (Box 70, Folder 27)
    - Jones, Granville L., M.D., "Occupational and Recreational Therapy," 1949. (Box 70, Folder 28)
    - Jones, Granville L., M.D., "The History of the Founding of the Eastern State Hospital of Virginia," in American Journal of Psychiatry, 1954. (Box 70, Folder 29)
    - Journal of the American Medical Association, "Selected Papers from the 61st Annual Congress on Medical Education," 1965. (Box 70, Folder 30)
    - King, Lucy J., M.D., "A Brief History of Psychiatry: Millenia Past and Present," Parts I-III, in Annals of Clinical Psychiatry, 1999. (Box 70, Folder 31)
    - Kline, Martin S., et. al., "Administrative Support is Important for a Successful Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program in a Public Psychiatric Hospital," in Administration and Policy in Mental Health, 2002. (Box 70, Folder 32)
    - Levenson, James L., M.D., and Fisher, John G., M.D., "Long-term Outcomes after Neuroleptic Malignant Syndrome," undated. (Box 70, Folder 33)
    - Longo, Daniele A., et. al., "Psychosocial Rehabilitation in a Public Psychiatric Hospital," in Psychiatric Quarterly, 2002. (Box 70, Folder 34)
    - Longo, Daniele A. and Peterson, Stephanie M., "The Role of Spirituality in Psychosocial Rehabilitation," in Psychiatric Rehabilitation Journal, 2002. (Box 70, Folder 35)
    - Mazzarella, Deborah J. and Marsh-Williams, Karen, "Creating a New Culture: Establishing a Transitional Living Community at a State Hospital," in International Journal of Psychosocial Rehabilitation, 2005. (Box 70, Folder 36)
    - Morrisey, Dr. Joseph P. and Goldman, Howard H., M.D., "Cycles of Reform in the Care of the Chronically Mentally Ill," in Hospital and Community Psychiatry, 1984. (Box 70, Folder 37)
    - National Library of Medicine, "Medicine of the Civil War," undated. (Box 70, Folder 38)
    - National Society for Autistic Children, "Collection of Papers Deriving from the Course of Lectures on the Education of Autistic Children Held at the Society School for Autistic Children in Autumn 1967," 1968. (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - Pile, Wendell J., M.D., "Effect of Glutamic Acid on Chronic Psychotic Patients," in Diseases of the Nervous System, 1952. (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - Ravitz, Leonard J., M.D., "Application of the Electrodynamic Field Theory in Biology, Psychiatry, Medicine and Hypnosis," in American Journal of Clinical Hypnosis, 1959. (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - Ravitz, Leonard J., M.D., "How Electricity Measures Hypnosis," in Tomorrow, 1958. (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - Riese, Walther, M.D., et. al., "Disseminated Demyelinating Process of Over 50 Years Duration First Seen by Dr. William Osler," in Confinia Neurologica, 1952. (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - Riese, Walther, M.D., "Marchiafava-Bignami's Disease: Report of a Second Case in Native-Born Americans," in Journal of Neuropathology and Experimental Neurology, 1954. (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Roebuck, Basil E., "Agranulocytosis Associated with Chlorpromazine Therapy," in The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, 1956. (Box 71, Folder 7)
    - Roebuck, Basil E., et. al., "An Evaluation of the Therapeutic Use of Triflupromazine in Mental Disease," in The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, 1959. (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - Ruth, Alfred E.H., "The Many Roles of the Mental Hospital," in Information Bulletin No. VI., undated, circa 1960. (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - Stratas, N.E., M.D., and Schmidt, K.T., M.D., "A Children's Unit in a State Hospital," in The American Journal of Psychiatry, 1960. (Box 71, Folder 10)
    - Tate, Frederic B., "Symbols in the Graphic Art of the Dying," in The Arts in Psychotherapy, 1989. (Box 71, Folder 11)
    - Tate, Frederic B. and Allen, Harry, "Color Preferences and the Aged Individual: Implications for Art Therapy," in The Arts in Psychotherapy, 1985. (Box 71, Folder 12)
    - Tate, Frederic B. and Longo, Dan A., "Art Therapy: Enhancing Psychosocial Nursing," in Journal of Psychosocial Nursing, 2002. (Box 71, Folder 13)
    - Tate, Frederic B. and Longo, Dan A., "HIV/AIDS Prevention: A Model for Educating the Inpatient Psychiatric Population," in AIDS Patient Care and STDs, 2000. (Box 71, Folder 14)
    - Tate, Frederic B. and Longo, Daniel A., "Homophobia: A Challenge for Psychosocial Nursing," in Journal of Psychosocial Nursing, 2004. (Box 71, Folder 15)
    - Tate, Frederic B. and Longo, Daniele A., "Death and Dying: Implications for Inpatient, Psychiatric Care," in Palliative and Supportive Care, 2005. (Box 71, Folder 16)
    - Tate, Frederic B. and Longo, Daniele A., "Safer Sex Education: Evaluating Effectiveness with Test Scores," in AIDS Patient Care and STDs, 2002. (Box 71, Folder 17)
    - Thompson, Jean M., "Eastern State Hospital: 200 Years of Caring," in Virginia Record, 1973. (Box 71, Folder 18)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Public Health Monograph No. 32, "Disposition of First Admissions to a State Mental Hospital," 1955. (Box 71, Folder 19)
    - Veterans Administration, "A Hypothesis of Schizophrenic Behavior," 1951. (Box 71, Folder 20)
    - Veterans Administration, "Elements of Psychotherapy in General Medical Practice," 1953. (Box 71, Folder 21)
    - Virginia Council on Health and Medical Care, Special Report No. 1, "Virginia Citizens Find Mental Hospitals in Urgent Need," 1949. (Box 71, Folder 22)
    - Ward, Rev. Archibald F., Jr., "The Role of the Chaplain in Patient Relationships: Individual Therapy," in The Journal of Pastoral Care, 1952. (Box 71, Folder 23)
    - Weimerskirch, Phillip J., "Benjamin Rush and John Minson Galt, II.,: Pioneers of Bibliotherapy in America," 1964. (Box 71, Folder 24)
    - Zwelling, Shomer S., "Inside the Public Hospital," in Colonial Williamsburg, 1985. (Box 71, Folder 25)
  - Subseries B. Journals, Periodicals, and Books, 1844-1985., Extent: .9 cu. ft. (Box 71-73.)
    Contains journals, periodicals and books related to mental illness generally, as well as specifically in Virginia. Advance and Mental Health in Virginia were published by the Virginia Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation and the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals respectively. Mental Hygiene Survey was published by the State Hospital Board and Virginia Medical Monthly was published by the Medical Society of Virginia. Also included are a book on Galt family genealogy, a book about the Willard Asylum in New York, and other periodicals unrelated to mental health that were found in the collection.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of journal and then chronologically within for those with multiple editions.
    - Advance, vol. 23, no. 5, 1973 September-October. (Box 71, Folder 26)
    - Advance, vol. 30, no. 2, 1980 Spring. (Box 71, Folder 27)
    - Advance, vol. 31, no. 3, 1981 Summer-Fall. (Box 71, Folder 28)
    - Advance Notice, vol. 2, issue 2, 1980 June. (Box 71, Folder 29)
    - Advance Notice, vol. 3, issue 1, 1981 February. (Box 71, Folder 30)
    - Colonial Williamsburg vol. VII,, no. 3 (devoted to The Public Hospital), 1985 Spring. (Box 71, Folder 31)
    - Diseases of the Nervous System, vol. 3, no. 1, 1942 January. (Box 71, Folder 32)
    - Mental Hygiene Survey, vol. 9, nos. 1-5, 1946 July-November. (Box 71, Folder 33)
    - Mental Hygiene Survey, vol. 9, nos. 7-9, 1947 January-March. (Box 71, Folder 34)
    - Mental Hygiene Survey, vol. 9, nos. 10-12, 1947 April-June. (Box 71, Folder 35)
    - Mental Hygiene Survey, vol. 10, nos. 1 and 7-8, 1947 July-1948 February. (Box 71, Folder 36)
    - Mental Hygiene Survey, vol. 11, nos. 1-3, 1948 July-September. (Box 71, Folder 37)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 4, no. 4, 1954 Summer. (Box 71, Folder 38)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 6, no. 3, 1955 Spring. (Box 71, Folder 39)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 9, no. 1, 1958 Autumn. (Box 71, Folder 40)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 10, no. 1, 1959 Autumn. (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 10, nos. 2-4, 1960. (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 11, nos. 1-4, 1960 Autumn-1961 Spring. (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 12, nos. 1-4, 1961 Autumn-1962 Summer. (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 14, no. 2, 1962-1963. (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 12, no. 3, 1963 Spring. (Box 72, Folder 6)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, "Into a Second Century of Service," (Central State Hospital), circa 1965. (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 17, no. 3, 1967 Spring. (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 18, no. 2, 1968 Winter. (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 18, no. 3, 1968 Spring. (Box 72, Folder 10)
    - Mental Health in Virginia, vol. 20, nos. 1, 3 and 4, 1969 Fall-1970 Spring. (Box 72, Folder 11)
    - Pictorial Album of the Willard Asylum, 1980. (Box 72, Folder 12)
    - The American Journal of Insanity, vol. I, no. 1 (modern reprint), 1844. (Box 72, Folder 13)
    - The American Journal of Insanity, vol. III, no. 3, 1847. (Box 72, Folder 14)
    - The American Journal of Insanity, vol. VI, no. 2, 1849. (Box 72, Folder 15)
    - The American Psychological Journal, vol. I, no. 3, 1853. (Box 72, Folder 16)
    - The Galt Families: Notes on their Origin and their History with Genealogical Lists, by Howard S. Galt, 1938. (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - The Industrial South, 1886 February-March. (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - The Medical News, vol. XVII (fragment), 1859. (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Medical Monthly, vol. 68, no. 9, 1941 September. (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Medical Monthly, "Mental Health" column and reprinted articles, 1951-1957. (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Medical Monthly, "Mental Health" column and reprinted articles, 1958-1959. (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Virginia Medical Monthly, "Mental Health" column and reprinted articles, 1960-1962. (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Medical Monthly, "Mental Health" column and reprinted articles, 1963-1965. (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Medical Monthly, "Mental Health" column and reprinted articles, 1966-1967. (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Medical Monthly, "Mental Health" column and reprinted articles, 1968-1974. (Box 73, Folder 10)
- Series XVI. Reports, 1842-1994., Extent: 3.9 cu. ft., 2 volumes. (Box 74-82;, Volume 155-156.)
  Contains two subseries of reports: annual and miscellaneous. The annual reports were produced by the Auditor of Public Accounts, the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals, Eastern State Hospital, the State Hospital Board, and Western Lunatic Asylum. The annual reports contain administrative, financial and operational information for each entity. The miscellaneous reports come from a variety of sources and document particular aspects of the mental health system in Virginia. Topics include progress reports, civil commitment, community services, and general surveys.
  - Subseries A. Annual Reports, 1842-1980., Extent: 3.15 cu. ft. (Box 74-80;, Volume 155.)
    Contains annual reports for Eastern State Hospital, Western State Hospital, the State Hospital Board and the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals. Also included is one volume containing the annual report of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts.
    - Auditor of Public Accounts, 1886. (Volume 155.)
      Contains annual report of the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts. Reports contain finanicial information for each state agency funded by the Commonwealth of Virginia. All annual reports submitted to the Auditor were compiled into one volume.
      - 1886. (Volume 155)
    - Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals, 1951-1968. (Box 74.)
      Contains annual reports the Virginia Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals. These reports document the year in review for the entire state agency under which the state hospitals operate. The reports often contain statistical and financial information for each institution under its governance, as well.
      - 1951. (Box 74, Folder 1)
      - 1952. (Box 74, Folder 2)
      - 1953. (Box 74, Folder 3)
      - 1955-1956. (Box 74, Folder 4)
      - 1967-1968. (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Eastern State Hospital, 1842-1980. (Box 74-77.)